welcome to the complete guide to editing
inside a final cut pro 10 for beginners
so if you're brand new to this software
then this is going to be the perfect
video for you i'm going to walk you
through everything that you need to know
to get started so you can start making
videos in final cut pro 10. this is
definitely a video that i wish i had
when i was starting out this would have
saved me so much time if i could have
watched a video like this in this video
i share a lot of practical tips for
editing not just do i show you how to
edit but i actually share with you how
to edit faster tips for improving your
editing and i show you some really cool
effects that you can do inside of final
cut pro 10. so we all know this is a
paid for software and i want to show you
all the cool things that you can do in
this as a beginner to really utilize
this program i'm going to show you how
to color grade your footage to make it
look better as well as editing audio to
make your audio sound as good as
possible with that all being said let's
get right into the master class you
gotta just press record hey guys my name
is noel noel with think media now make
sure you like this video and save this
video to a playlist so that you can
always come back to this video if you
need to i'm gonna cover a whole lot in
this video and you're probably not gonna
pick up every single thing the first
time watching this video it's going to
take practice and you may need to come
back and refer to this video so save it
to a playlist and we could just hang out
again now in this first section of the
video i'm going to show you how to open
up final cut pro 10 how to actually
start a project and get your footage
inside the software i'm gonna give you a
little virtual tour of final cut as well
as some basics to start editing video so
let's get into the first section where
we cover all of the basics right now now
before we even open up final cut pro we
do want to get our footage whether
that's on an sd card or your phone onto
your computer so if you do have an sd
card which looks like this you can plug
that into your computer if your computer
does not have an sd card slot you can
get an adapter we'll have links for all
these resources in the description down
below if you have something like an
iphone you can actually airdrop it
straight onto your computer but you want
to stay organized so we're going to
create a folder on our desktop right
here and i actually have an sd card so
this is my sd card right here i'll go
into dcim and right here i have some
fuji footage over here and just on my
computer in my movies folder i have
think media videos and i'm gonna create
a brand new folder and we're gonna title
this uh final cut tutorial obviously for
your name you can name it whatever you'd
like that's easy to remember for the
project that you are working on at this
point we are going to select the footage
from our sd card which is over here i'm
going to hold down shift after selecting
the top one and then select the bottom
one i'm going to drag that over my final
cut tutorial up here we get this loading
bar it's going to take a few minutes to
copy all our videos over onto our folder
and then up next we are going to import
that into final cut pro x the reason i
like to do this is kind of as a backup
so having the actual videos on your
computer if something does go wrong and
you happen to lose your footage somehow
or you accidentally delete it then you
still have those original files on the
sd card and you can easily re-link those
inside the software so that's why i like
to always copy my footage onto my
computer first or you can use something
like a samsung t5 hard drive and you can
edit straight off of that but to keep
things simple we're just going to keep
everything on the computer all right now
that our videos are in our folder we can
actually open up this folder make sure
they're all in there and what we can do
too is make a new folder and we can
title this videos and that way maybe
when we download some music and we want
to add that into our project we can
always come back to this folder we can
make a new folder called music we can
put all our music in here we can do the
same for images maybe one for b-roll and
a-roll if you want to separate your
videos but this keeps everything
organized and that's what i do for my
projects is i have different folders for
all my assets in the video so having
those folders really keeps me organized
if i ever go back to that project i
don't have missing files so it's
definitely something you want to get in
the habit of doing now let's open up
final cut pro x if you just downloaded
it or installed it or if you want to you
can get a 90 day free trial we'll have a
link in the description when you first
install it you're going to want to go
down here and open up your launchpad on
your launchpad you are going to see your
app somewhere over here mine is on the
second page right here and if you want
to bring it down here you just can drag
it and this will put it inside of this
little dock so that way it's easy to
access you can just go down here and hit
final cut pro and double tap it and this
is going to open up the software now
this is what it looks like when you
first open it up and the first step to
do to import our footage is create a
library on this left side over here we
see that this is where a library would
go but since we don't have one we're
gonna go to file we're going to go to
new and we're going to select library
for the name i just like to leave it as
the same name as my project so i'll just
do you know final cut tutorial it
doesn't even have to be the same it
doesn't really matter but to keep
organized we are going to place it in
the same folder so in movies and think
media videos i'm going to add final cut
tutorial and i'm just going to put it
inside of this folder we'll hit save and
now if i go back to that folder you are
going to see that we have a library
right here this library is going to hold
everything so if you ever need to get
back in there and edit you can actually
go right in here you can double click
this and it's going to open up that
library with the videos that you have in
there right here is where you have an
event and this is where you're going to
upload some of that footage we click on
it once we can rename it and we are just
going to call this fuji footage and that
way i can upload all my fuji footage in
here and it's really easy to know that
this is where my fuji footage is with
that selected we're going to hit import
media and this is going to open up our
media import tab i'm gonna find my
footage by going to nolan mold then
going to movies and then think media
videos right here is my final cut
tutorial and if i select that it's
actually just going to import everything
inside of this folder obviously the
library can't be imported but i do have
my video in there so i'm just going to
select that and then over here we have a
lot of options on this right hand side
we can see right here that it's going to
add to our existing event fuji footage
which we just made and then as far as
files go you want to leave files in
place if you copy to the library your
library is going to get very large and i
actually just like to keep everything
separate and in my own folders and so
this is the way i do it to stay
organized if you copy it to the library
you can do that as well but things seem
to be a bit less organized when i do
that as far as keywords go we can leave
both of those checked and then for
analyze video i like to leave both of
these unchecked for transcode under
optimized media if you have some weird
file sizes this is going to make it more
compatible with final cut pro by making
it a pro res file or you can create
proxy medias which is what i like to use
so if you have a slow computer you can
create a proxy media and basically it's
a low resolution file size and so it's a
lot smaller files and they run a lot
faster on your computer and then you can
sub those out when you start editing and
then when you go to export your final
project you basically replace your
hi-res whether it's 4k or just even 1080
and then your final edit is going to
have those original files back in place
but it makes the editing so much easier
and so much faster especially if you
have a slow computer so i'm going to
select create proxy media and for my
codec prores proxy is going to work fine
h.264 will work as well but i like to
use the prores proxies frame size i'm
going to leave at 50
and after that we're just going to hit
import all now we can see that we have
footage inside of final cut pro and up
here we have a loading bar so if we
select this this is actually going to
show us the background tasks that are
happening right now there is transcoding
and analysis that just means that it's
creating the proxy files for us if we
click this down it's transcoding making
the proxy clips for each of these clips
right now now as that runs in the
background we can carry on now in order
to start editing we need a project so
events are kind of what carries your
music your pictures your videos and your
project is your edit it's where the
videos and all the files will go into
you'll mess around with them and that
project is what you'll export and again
the library is what holds everything to
create a new project we'll go to file
new and select project for our project
name i'll just name it final cut
tutorial it's going to be in the event
fuji footage which is perfect for me and
for video i'm going to leave it at 4k
but if you shot in 1080 then hit 1080p
hd but for me mine is in 4k and this is
the correct resolution for frame rate i
actually shot in 23.98 frames per second
uh rendering codec all this stuff is
fine color space is fine audio all that
stuff you won't need to touch from there
you'll hit ok and right up here you'll
now see we have a project also down here
we can now move this playhead because we
have a project and this is our project
timeline this is where we are going to
edit everything back up here in the
vents where we have our videos you can
see we can scrub through here and this
is going to allow us to view this
footage even before we add it to our
project if you scrub over your video and
hit the space bar this is actually going
to play it for you so let's say all
right this is the clip i want to use you
can either select it once and drag it
into your timeline or let me delete that
now let's say you just want to use the
second half of this clip you can
actually drag this and just bring down
that second half of the clip or what you
could do is just bring the entire clip
down and trim it down here while it's
already in the timeline if you hold down
shift you can select all your clips and
just throw those in the timeline and
edit it from there i do this a lot of
the time i just throw them all in and
then i start editing inside of my
project with some videos on the timeline
if you select one of these clips over
here we have our effect so if this is
not popping up yet you can click this
button right here and that's going to
bring up your effects if you want to add
a transition you can actually click this
one and this is going to be your
transitions and it's as simple as
dragging and dropping so let's say we
want to use this cross dissolve i'll
drag this over the second clip and right
now it's going to say there's not enough
extra media just hit create transition
and this is going to transition a cross
dissolve between the two clips
and if you want to delete that you can
just select your transition and hit
delete and that's going to get rid of
that transition back over here on
effects you can do the same thing you
can drag an effect right here and now
you have a 50s tv effect and if you want
to delete an effect you can select your
clip up here in the right hand corner
this is your properties right now at the
top we see effects we can just select
50s tv and delete that so over here on
the right hand side this is all your
information about your clip or maybe
your audio so you can see over here we
can mess with our opacity we can change
that uh transform is like the
positioning and so you can move that
around you can also scale your image by
dragging the slider or you can select
the scale and maybe you want to make it
200 you can do that as well now what i
like to do what i think is a lot easier
is right down here we have this little
drop down menu you can do a transform
tool and this is your scale right here
you can move the positioning around you
can scale it up or down you know do
whatever you want to do with that to
reset this all you got to do is go back
up here and hit reset and that's going
to put everything back to normal for
your transform tool if we change this to
crop this allows us to crop in on an
image or crop out on an image and trim
allows you to actually trim off an image
so if you want to make it more of a
square image add something else in there
you know you can do that with trim
another important thing to look at on
this viewer window is this percentage
right here so we have the 70
if we want to make that 50
this actually isn't changing the scale
or anything like that it's just changing
the size of it inside of our software so
if i want to make this as big as
possible for this window i would just
hit fit and that is going to fit it in
here so as i move these around if i want
to make this bigger this is just
automatically going to make it smaller
for me or make it bigger if i make the
window bigger so to recap down here is
where we are going to edit our project
up here is all of our videos so to
actually get these onto your project you
have to bring them down into the
timeline but this is where they all are
so if i delete some of these they are
still going to be up here they're not on
the project they're not on the final
video but it's not like i'm deleting
them out of the software if i want to
put them back in i can by just dragging
it back onto the timeline over here we
have our event as well as our library
and you can create new events if you
want to maybe you have like a part two
or day two and you wanna separate the
days uh you could do that by just naming
it day two and then you have a brand new
event so if you see no footage you might
be on the wrong event you need to go to
a different event where you have your
project you have your other footage but
this also allows you to organize things
inside of final cut if that makes it
easier for you typically i just keep
everything inside of one event so i have
nine clips in my events folder right
here and i'm gonna drag all of these
onto my timeline i'm holding down shift
and select this last one i'm just gonna
simply drag those and now i have all my
videos inside of my project i'm gonna
zoom in a little bit here so i can see
what's going on to do that you can hit
command plus button or if you hit
command minus button this is going to
zoom out now editing is as simple as
removing clips and keeping the good
stuff so that's what we're gonna do
first we're gonna go through and start
removing some of the pieces that we
don't want in our final video so to hit
play so far on my video i'll hit the
space bar i'm just looking at the camera
kind of getting ready to talk and if i
zoom in on this clip right here you see
these audio waveforms down here this is
when i start talking and this is when i
want the video to start when i actually
start saying stuff also you might notice
there's this black vignetting on these
corners on this camera i'm going to show
you how to fix that how to kind of crop
in a little bit we'll do that next but
first this is what you're going to use
most of the time which is your blade
tool to pull up your blade tool you can
go over here and you can select the
blade or you could hit b but this is
kind of your tool so you have select you
can trim position range selection but i
just like to learn these shortcuts and
so i will hit b and you can see right
here now my cursor is a blade all you
have to do is select where you want to
make your cut and when you click on that
you can see that there's now a splice
right in between these videos so now we
have one cut in the video kind of making
it two videos so we can select this
first part and if we hit delete now the
beginning of this video starts when i
start talking let's go to the end of
this clip and do the same thing over
here so i'm talking and this is where
i'm going to end it now if you hit
command b this is going to make a cut
for you right where your playhead is and
so this right here is the playhead so
where your playhead is is where it's
going to start playing your video so
with over there i hit command b and this
is what happened i'll select the second
half of the clip and i will delete that
now that right there is a big piece of
editing just kind of getting rid of the
parts that you don't want and keeping
all the good stuff another thing you can
do here if you want to extend this clip
or maybe shorten it is hover over the
end of the clip and you're going to see
this trim tool now if you hold down if
you click and hold down you can drag
this to the left to start cutting off
more of this clip on the left if you
want to extend it you can drag it to the
right now if i want to do the same thing
on the right clip i'm going to slightly
move it to the right and now you see
that bracket has flipped now this means
i am trimming this right clip so i can
extend it to the left but this red
marker lets me know this is the
beginning of the clip so i'm going to
start cutting everything out that i
don't want and i want it to start right
there let's bring this clip back and
that is allowing you to trim those so
that you can extend them shorten them
lengthen them do what you want with that
i use that tool a whole lot as well now
let's say i want this clip actually to
go first before this very first clip all
you have to do is select the clip you
want to move you can drag it and we're
going to drag that right in front and
now everything kind of snaps into place
now this clip is going to play first and
this clip is now going to play second
now let's say we want to add an effect
over here we have our effects window and
let's say we want to add the camcorder
so i'm going to drag that onto this clip
here and now you're going to see that we
have this camcorder effect just by
dragging that now if i select this clip
over here in the inspector tool we can
mess with the amount of this effects
being added we'll leave that at 100 you
can change the text to whatever you want
to say let's say think the size all this
stuff is adjustable so if you ever want
to adjust something go over here into
the effects tab make sure you have your
effect selected and then you can mess
with some of these effects now let's add
a transition so i'm going to go over to
my transitions by clicking this and we
are going to let's say this circle one
we are going to drag this right in
between these two clips now let's play
it through and see how it looks
so it's pretty cool but let's say i want
to speed it up and make it a faster
transition all you need to do is trim
and shorten up that transition so with a
trim tool just like we were making a
clip shorter we're going to use this to
make our transition sorter so with the
bracket facing the right way to the left
we know that we are selecting this uh
transition so we are going to bring that
in and that brings in both sides for us
now it's a quicker transition and if you
want to make it extra long you can drag
that out and this now has your
transition being extra long
now let's say you want to move the
transition a little bit to the left or
the right so it starts earlier or maybe
it starts later if you hover over the
middle you can actually move this
transition let's say we want it to start
sooner this is going to cut off what we
were just having but let's say we wanted
to cut off that anyways that's how you
can move the transition within the clip
to play earlier or later let's say we
like it right here but we don't want all
this dead space all you need to do is
hit b to bring up your blade tool we are
going to cut right there then we're
going to delete this clip and now it's
going to start when i start talking all
right let's get rid of this vignette
that i was telling you guys about the
dark corners all you got to do is crop
in so with your clip selected if you go
right here we are going to change this
from trim to crop now i can actually
crop in on my clip so i'm going to make
sure that this vignette is not showing
by zooming in a bit and then we are
going to reposition where we want it
when we're done we're going to hit done
now we've actually cropped in on the
image so that we're not seeing the
vignetting and you can crop in on any
clip i use this a lot to kind of crop in
on my face crop it back out so this is a
great tool to use and to know how to use
now if we want to mess with the audio
and make the audio louder on this
specific clip we can hover over this
line right here if we hover over this
line we are going to see 0.0 db this is
the standard the neutral place for your
audio to be at so as you import any sort
of audio as you import any sort of video
it's going to start at 0 db you can then
add plus 2 plus 12 db minus 12 db you
can mess around and add or take away
from the volume so we are going to
increase the volume i'm simply just
going to drag up this line right here
and this is going to actually boost up
those waveforms you can see that now it
says 5 db and if you don't have your
audio waveforms right here all you got
to do is select this and this is going
to bring them up for you so now when i
play my clip it's going to be louder
than it was before and if i want to
completely silence it i can bring that
to zero you can see there's no audio
happening right here and then i can
bring the audio back up i'm like okay i
want it right around
9 db perfect this is exactly where i
want it and that's how you can adjust
the volume now if we want to add text up
here we have our test and generator so
i'm going to select this we have titles
and we have generators generators are
kind of like backgrounds is how i would
explain them so one i use a lot is just
a custom which is a color and then from
here we can change the color to whatever
we want so let's say we want the color
to be white i'll drag this like that now
i have a white background and i can add
text to this and so we'll go over to
titles now these different titles have
different effects we can see this one is
dramatic and if i hover over from left
to right we're going to see kind of the
effect that it does and if you like one
you can simply drag it onto your clip
clearly it's a white text over white
background so we can't see it so what
we'll do is first let's change the face
which is going to be the color and so
we're going to hit show and we are going
to change the color to let's change it
to a blue now if you want to change your
text you can just double click on title
and this is going to highlight
everything for you now we have this text
bubble popped up so we'll change this to
think media and now let's play this
through to see how it looks
now the one i typically use is just a
custom and this is just your basic text
so let's change this text to black and
now up here we have this text so we can
change this to think media we can change
the font if we want you can move around
by dragging this here you can also
change the font size mess with any of
the properties all under here under this
properties tab back on the timeline if
we just want to delete a clip i'm like
okay i don't really want this in there
you can select the whole thing you can
delete this and then up here if you want
to use it again you can bring it back
you can see that there's an orange
underlined this means i'm using the clip
right now on my timeline this makes it
really easy to see the clips that you
haven't used yet and so i can hover over
it and see if i want to bring that back
in so if you delete something in your
project it's still going to be there in
your event and then from there you can
just bring it back into your project if
you'd like now if you aren't seeing
these orange lines all you need to do is
go to view go to browser and make sure
that used media ranges is selected now
in order to use some music let's import
it into final cut pro first we're gonna
right click right here and we're gonna
hit import media i have a song on my
desktop so i'm gonna select that song
and then hit import selected from here
i'm gonna drag this entire song down
here onto my timeline we can do the same
thing with audio that we can with video
so if we want to trim this then we can
do that if we want to lower the audio
then we can definitely do that by
bringing that down i'll then drag this
to the beginning of the project and then
if i want to fade in the audio so it
doesn't start abruptly there is a little
ball right here and if you drag that to
the right this is going to be a fade in
for your music and you can also do this
on videos by just dragging these to the
right this is going to fade in your
audio so that doesn't start abruptly but
it just fades in you can also fade out
your audio by doing the same thing on
the other end congratulations you now
have the basics to start editing videos
but there is a whole lot more to learn
stuff that's going to make your life
easier stuff that's going to make your
videos a lot better and one of those
things is audio editing your audio to
sound as good as possible as well as
learning you know how loud your video
should be are very simple things that i
can teach you and i'm going to teach you
right now with the basics of audio
editing but first i want to remind you
that i cover a whole lot in this video
yes this is for beginners but there
still is a lot to go over for example in
this audio section that we're going to
go over i show you how to use the
equalization to make your microphone
sound as good as possible do you
actually have to do this for your
beginning videos no not really but this
is something that you should do over
time so once you're comfortable just
starting to edit videos and getting that
process these are things that i wish i
knew when i was a beginner because these
are things that are going to level up
your audio your video all this stuff as
quick as possible but with that being
said let's jump right into audio editing
now before we get into this tutorial
it's definitely recommended to wear
headphones when you are audio editing
typically your headphones are going to
be so much better to listen to audio
than something like a built-in computer
speaker or a monitor speaker most people
don't have expensive speakers but they
do have some headphones laying around so
plug those in and that's gonna be better
off for you to start editing your audio
so here in final cut pro 10 you can see
that i do have some clips down here and
we are going to be editing the audio of
these video clips to make it sound as
good as possible i'm going to walk you
through everything that i do step by
step so you guys can see exactly my
process not saying that my process is
the best process but if you are a
beginner i promise you you are going to
learn a few things here that are going
to make your audio sound a lot better so
stay to the end of this video so you do
not miss out but the first thing that i
like to do is actually the eq now this
is something that i didn't do for a long
time because i was just kind of
overwhelmed with it and to be honest i'm
not a professional when it comes to
doing this so i'm going to show you what
i do and i'm going to try and teach it
in a basic way that a beginner could
follow and understand and practice some
of this stuff in your own video so let's
get right into it first thing we want to
do is to select a clip that we want to
edit so i'm gonna go ahead and select
this first clip and if we hit play we
can hear that the audio link to this
audio right now then you are hearing me
sounds fine but it's a little bit low we
are going to fix that next but i am
going to adjust the eq first and then
you'll see why i do that first later but
what we do is we go up here and we are
going to see this little sound mixer box
this sound mixer box if we click this
it's going to open up see equalization
it's going to open up this window right
here this is called the graphic
equalizer right now it's set to flat and
you can see that each point is set to
zero decibels now if i raise this point
which is 32 hertz this is going to be 12
decibels and that's going to raise that
lower bassy frequency up higher so that
it's louder or i could reduce that to
negative 20 db and that is going to make
it very very quiet so each of these
decibels are related to a different uh
hurts a different frequency dragging
them up are going to emphasize that make
them louder dragging them down are going
to get rid of that now the reason i use
this is to actually make my audio sound
better so i adjust these up and down and
it can actually make your microphone
sound a lot cleaner a lot smoother and
sometimes when recording on dslrs or
mirrorless cameras it just doesn't sound
full it doesn't sound super good and
actually just messing with this a little
bit can make your voice sound a lot
cleaner and honestly can really make a
cheap microphone sound expensive if you
get this right like they can sound
really really good if you mess with
these settings correctly now what i like
to do is actually set this first clip on
a loop and it's really simple to do this
you need to make sure that your loop
playback is on all you got to do is hit
command l and that is going to turn it
on or if it's already on that would turn
it off but command l to turn it back on
and then instead of hitting the space
bar for play like we always do we're
going to hit this forward slash button
hitting this button is going to play it
and then put it on a loop so that it
goes over and over again and as it's
playing you're going to see me do a few
things here you're going to see me
moving this up and down seeing what
sounds better now typically voices don't
fall in this range or in this range it's
usually in that middle range and so
these i might be able to move around a
little bit but i won't really notice
much until i get into this range of the
eq another thing i'm looking for here is
the background ac unit there is a noise
removal plug-in that i'm going to show
you guys how to use but actually messing
with this i might be able to find that
maybe the ac is on a specific
channel frequency and if i pull it down
it's going to get rid of that so i'm
looking to get rid of some of those
unwanted noises by lowering the
frequency and then i'm looking to kind
of mess with the rest of them to get my
voice sounding as clear and full as
possible so we're gonna go ahead and
loop this and then i am going to mess
with the eq
if you're listening to this audio right
now then you are hearing me edit this
audio to make it sound better if you're
listening to this audio right now then
you are hearing me edit this audio to
make it sound better so right here you
can see as i pulled this up it's
actually increasing the ac unit in the
background so i definitely don't want to
do that and by the way you never want to
boost any of these up to 20 decibels i
usually boost them if i'm going to boost
them around the six decibel mark
but you do not want to go that high but
the reason i'm doing that now is so i
can hear it better and i go okay this is
where the ac unit is falling in
and so these are the kind of things that
i'm listening for while editing
listening to this audio right now then
you are hearing me edit this audio to
make it sound better all right now in
this channel i'm also really getting
that ac unit as well i'm going to hit
play so you guys can hear that now then
you are hearing me edit this audio to
make it sound better now instead of just
reducing this all the way to get rid of
that noise this ac unit sound is
actually tied to some of the same
frequencies as my voice so it's gonna
sound a bit funny if i just pull this
all the way down you're listening to
this audio right now it sounds pretty
dead my voice kind of sounds like it's
coming through a telephone or a
walkie-talkie so this is where you
really have to kind of play back and
forth go through it a few times and see
what's going to sound best because you
want to take away some of those noises
you don't want but you also want your
voice sounding really nice
audio to make it sound better if you're
listening to this audio right now then
you are hearing me edit this so in this
channel i feel like as i pull it up i'm
starting to get that walkie-talkie
telephone effect again and it's making
my voice just sound a lot less
full and so bringing that up i
definitely don't want to do i'm going to
leave it at zero i could even bring it
down a little bit if i don't want that
but for now i'm gonna leave it at zero
and move on to the next one
if you're listening to this audio right
now then you are hearing me edit this
audio to make it sound better if you're
listening to this audio right now then
you are hearing me edit this audio to
make it sound better if you're listening
to this audio right now then you are
hearing me edit this audio to make it
sound better if you're listening to this
audio right now then you are hearing me
edit this audio to make it now once i've
gone through i made some simple
adjustments i'll put it on loop and i'll
kind of click it on and off to see how
it sounds if it's if it's starting to
sound worse then i'm doing something
wrong if it's starting to sound better
i'm on the right track what i'll do is
i'll go back through these again and
i'll start to just tweak them little by
little until i get something that i'm
happy with you are hearing me edit this
audio to make it sound better if you're
listening to this audio right now then
you are hearing
so i definitely feel with it on i am
getting less of that ac unit sound in
the background and i feel like my voice
is a little bit fuller there's a few
things i can tweak here so i'm going to
play it through a couple more times and
just make some small tweaks to the eq
if you're listening to this audio right
now then you are hearing me edit this
audio now it's just a subtle difference
but i do definitely think this sounds a
whole lot better and so i'm pretty happy
with how this is sounding once i'm done
all you got to do is hit that x and this
is going to save everything so i'm going
to hit x and now what i can do is i can
see over here and turn off and on just
from this tab right here if i do want to
go back in and make some changes i can
click on that sound board again and this
is going to pull up the same window now
one thing that i like to add here and
there i don't use it all the time but i
do really like using it and it's helped
me a lot and that's the compressor now
to find it if you go to the effects tab
by clicking on this you are going to see
that it's set to video but if you scroll
down you are going to see audio and it
says all we can click on that and from
here we can search for compressor you
can drag that onto your clip now watch
what happens to the waveform when i let
go it's going to boost stuff up now the
compressor is really good for boosting
up low ends where stuff is quiet and
it's also good for not clipping those
high ends it tries to keep everything
together more level so here's a great
example when i was shooting my how to
vlog video with my wife we had one
shotgun microphone right in between us
but i just talked a little bit louder
than her so her audio was a lot quieter
and so when i threw the compressor on it
brought her voice up so that we were at
about the same audio level and that i
wasn't much louder than her but we both
had that same loudness now there's a
whole lot that you can do with
compressor if you open up the parameters
you can mess with all these and see
what's going to sound best for you
typically what i do sometimes is just
leave it how it is now this is the
beginner's tutorial so i am not going to
touch anything but you can see here even
the audio form looks a lot uh like a lot
more level it doesn't look like the low
parts are as low so if i listen to this
back things are going to sound a lot
louder that work quieter and so you can
hear what that sounds like if you're
listening to this audio right now then
you are hearing me edit this audio to
make it sound better now again i don't
always love using the compressor because
what i found is sometimes when you are
quiet and it boosts stuff up it can
boost up that background noise like the
ac or other things like that so
definitely something to experiment with
but it can be a lifesaver like it was
for me on that video with my wife and
ended up sounding really really good for
this clip i'm actually going to remove
that and my next step that i would do if
i was editing this is to set my audio
levels i like to do the compressor first
because that kind of messes with that
but setting the audio levels is really
simple all you need to do is drag this
up and down so you can see if i drag it
up to 12 db that's going to make it as
loud as possible or if i drag it down
that is going to make it quieter now
when setting your audio levels you want
to make sure that nothing is clipping
above this 0db
audio levels right here so if i play it
through i'm going to see where this is
falling i want it to fall right around
negative six uh even if it goes up above
that that's fine as long as it doesn't
pass over zero if you're listening to
this audio right now then you are
hearing me edit this audio to make it
sound better so it sounds pretty good i
honestly could increase that to uh you
know seven or eight but if you notice
something right here right right when i
tried to pull that up it just jumped up
to twelve well what you can do to do
precise adjustments is hold down the
command button and then when you do this
i can go from six to seven to eight
pretty easily because it slows
everything down so i'm gonna go ahead
and move that to seven and that is a
nice little hack that you can do one
other thing you can do is go up here and
you can actually just change your db by
typing this in if i want to go to 7.5 or
something you can do that
and you can also drag this as well i'm
going to leave mine at 7 db i'll do one
last check make sure it's not clipping
in this beginning part where it's nice
and loud and it looks perfect the next
thing that i might add is a noise
removal this can help get rid of that
background noise and so if i go up here
and i go to my audio analysis tab and i
click show this is going to give us some
more options and you can see right here
it says noise removal if i click that
it's automatically set to 50 and
typically this is a bit too much i find
that it kind of distorts the voice too
much it just doesn't sound the best so
we're gonna hit play and see how this
sounds at fifty percent you're listening
to this audio right now then you are
it's actually taking away from the
quality of the voice and so i am going
to bring this down
even though it did get rid of that
background noise and it's just my voice
you don't hear the ac at all
it's not worth it because it just
doesn't sound as good if you're
listening to this audio right now then
you are hearing me edit this audio to
make it sound better now then you are
hearing me edit this audio to make it
sound so what i found is right at 30 for
this clip uh specifically it gets rid of
that background noise without messing
with my voice a bunch and again i don't
even use this all the time because it
can mess with your voice so much and i
actually have a video on how to record
your audio with no background noise so
definitely check that out by clicking
the link in the description that's going
to save your life because you do not
want to be using this noise removal but
if you get into an instance where you
might need to this is always there to
help save you if you need it so let's
say that we like this audio and we want
to copy and paste it to all the clips in
the timeline what you can do is you can
click your clip you can hit command c
and then if you select both your other
clips if you hit shift command v this is
going to be paste attributes now the
other clips already have a color wheels
and a hue saturation on them i just want
to copy over these audio attributes so
i'm going to deselect everything on this
side and from this i can copy and paste
all this which looks great i'll hit
paste and now all my clips are going to
have the same audio everything that i
just changed on that first clip is now
on all my clips so i just drag some
music into my timeline and i have a few
more tips for you guys that's going to
help a lot with your videos and so first
off one major mistake that i see a lot
of people do is they add in their
background music way too loud and so i
like to start by bringing mine down all
the way to about negative 32 decibels
now really this is just by ear and
hearing how it sounds with your video
and obviously if like the chorus or the
drop happens in this in the song that
might need to come a little bit lower
but you just want to listen to this and
honestly i tell people you'd rather
under do it than overdo it because i've
clicked off videos before where the
background music was just too loud and
it's annoying so again you'd rather just
bring that a little bit too low than a
little bit too high if you're listening
to this audio right now then you are
hearing me edit this audio to make it
sound better now i can't even hear that
music so i'm going to actually bring
that up what i've noticed is that
usually the chorus or the loudest part
of the song that is going to be around
negative 32. sometimes these beginning
parts in in the video can be anywhere at
negative 16 negative 12 really just
depends on the song but that's just
something to listen for as you're
editing the music if you're listening to
this audio right now then you are
hearing me edit this audio to make it
sound better now like that sounds pretty
good right at negative 20 db it's just
in the background it's not overpowering
but we can see here as it starts to get
louder i'll show you guys how to
actually make that quieter so let's say
actually right at this part right here
we want to boost this part of the song
maybe there's going to be some b-roll or
something cool is happening and there's
no one talking so we just want to
increase the audio of the music so that
it kind of takes over the video now how
you do this is you can hit r and this is
going to bring up your range selector
and once you select how much you want of
this song to increase you can then drag
it back up like this most people want to
bring it to zero because that's how it
just imports as zero decibels but that
actually is going to be too loud because
when i'm talking you know how we
recorded stuff and it ends up being
around negative six decibels well that's
what i found is that you don't want your
music really going over negative six
decibels sometimes because it can just
sound really really loud compared to
your voice when you're talking you can
see that i also have some keyframes here
and you can totally move these around if
you want it to fade in slower or if you
want it to fade in really quickly you
can move these closer together and you
still can change the loudness right here
by dragging it up and down better and a
lot cleaner
[Music]
okay well i think that sounds pretty
good again this stuff is all by ear so
what i recommend is watching some videos
that you like on youtube listening to it
and hearing how their background music
comes in is it really loud is it really
quiet and try to match that in your
editing so let's say this is the end of
the video if you want to fade out the
music right here we are going to can't
see it right now with the playhead over
it but right here we're going to see
this little icon and if you drag this
over this allows you to fade out the
music so if i drag it over even more
it's going to fade out even slower this
would be a very quick fade out and so
this is what that sounds like if you
want to fade out the music
now same at the beginning i usually like
to fade in the beginning of my music
just a little bit and you can do that at
the beginning as well just by doing that
you can do the same thing with a video
clip so if i want to fade in the audio
of this video clip you can drag this in
as well you can do that on any clip
audio video you can fade it in or fade
it out now if you want to separate your
audio if you click on a video you can
right click and then you can detach the
audio and this is going to allow you to
extend this over and maybe fade it in
and then i can do the same thing with
this one as well and this is going to
allow your clips to be smoother as they
transition into each other especially if
you're talking quick and your cuts are
fast this is going to help from any sort
of weird pops that might happen if
you're like a frame off and it's cutting
off the very beginning of your word if
you detach your audio you can actually
extend that so that your word or
whatever you're saying is finishing and
you can also use this in many ways so
knowing how to detach the audio is a
very useful thing just right click
detach audio now i just found out about
this trick this last year and it's been
really really cool because i didn't even
know you could do this but i've loved
using that and that is soloing a track
so let's say you added in your music
maybe you have your sound effects you
have everything in but you want to edit
your audio you forgot to edit your audio
and that's fine you don't have to edit
your audio first when editing a video
but let's say you have all the sound
effects all this music and now it's time
for you to do the eq adjust the levels
well what you can do instead of playing
this with music over it like this audio
right now then you are hearing me you
can either select your audio clip and
hit v and that's going to disable this
clip so if i play this again here right
now then you are hearing me now all you
can hear is my voice i can click on the
clip i can edit the eq i can do whatever
i want to this clip but let's say
there's a bunch of sound effects and
maybe a whole bunch of other stuff
happening another way you can do this
let's go ahead and hit v on that again
another way you can do this is click on
the clip that you want to solo out and
then you can hit these headphones and
that is going to make everything else in
this timeline grayed out because it's
all muted and now all that you can hear
is the clip you have selected and you
can also select all the clips you want
let's say you want all the talking head
clips just to be selected you can select
all of those you can then hit the
headphone icon and that's going to work
as well the shortcut for this is option
s so let's say i want to select all my
talking head because i want to go ahead
and edit that audio i can hit option s
and that's going to disable everything
else so when i'm editing this audio all
i hear is my voice up next we have our
keyboard shortcuts now this is going to
save you a whole lot of time now i go
over a lot of keyboard shortcuts really
quickly so you might want to have a pen
and paper close by to write some of
these down but even just picking up a
few of these is going to make your life
so much easier and save you so much time
so here are my favorite keyboard
shortcuts for final cut pro 10. number
one is to hit b which is going to bring
up your blade tool and you can hover
over your video and select wherever
you'd like to make a cut to make this
even quicker if you hit command b it is
automatically going to cut for you
wherever your playhead is using command
b like this is going to make a cut on
the layer you have selected but if you
want to make a cut on all the layers on
top of your playhead you can do shift
command b and that is going to make cuts
on every single layer where your
playhead is at number two is to hit a
which is going to bring up your selector
tool and from there you can select the
clips that you want to delete and you
can go ahead and delete those number
three is to hit l this is going to start
your footage and when you hit it again
it's going to play back your video even
faster this makes it a lot easier to
watch back your videos at a faster speed
in order for you to save time when
editing freeze frames can be really cool
to add to your videos and it's really
easy in final cut pro 10 all you have to
do is hover over the spot where you want
it to freeze you will select your clip
and hit option f this is going to add in
a freeze frame you can drag it to the
left to make it shorter you can drag it
to the right to make it longer and when
you watch it back your freeze frame is
going to happen and then the rest of the
video is going to continue on once the
freeze frame is over when making precise
cuts in final cut pro 10 you want to
zoom into your timeline so you can see
everything going on usually what you do
is you go over here you click this
button and then you can zoom in like
this but a much quicker way to do this
is by hitting command plus and this is
going to zoom into your timeline and
then hitting command minus is going to
zoom out of your timeline i use this
tool all the time to zoom in and refine
my cuts and zooming in really just makes
it a whole lot easier right here we can
see that our audio is pretty quiet but
if you want to make your audio louder at
a certain point or quieter at a certain
point all you need to do is hit r and
this is going to pull up the range
selector this is going to work on an
audio or video clip you just need to
select a piece that you want to be
quieter or louder and from here once
that's selected all you got to do is
drag up on that audio making it louder
or you can make it softer you can then
drag these keyframes out a bit longer
for a smoother transition to the louder
part of the song
next up is shortcuts for copy cut and
paste i use these all the time so
knowing the shortcuts really comes in
handy to copy you just need to hit
command c if you want to cut you can hit
command x to paste the clip you can hit
command v or if you want to paste the
attributes like the effects the color
grade you can hit command option v and
that is going to add everything from
your clip to this next clip but let's
say you want to add everything but the
crop what you can do is hit shift
command v and this is going to paste
your attributes from here you can select
what you want to copy over to the next
clip or not so i want to add in all
these effects my entire color grade but
i don't want to add in my crop i'll
select that so it is not selected
anymore i'll go ahead i'll hit paste now
my color grade has copied over to this
clip without adding a crop now let's say
you've copied and pasted all your
effects onto all your clips in your
video but now you're going through and
you want to change something instead of
going through clip by clip and deleting
something like an eq what you can do is
select all the clips and now you're
going to hit shift command x and now you
can remove attributes and so i'm going
to select the eq get rid of that i'm
going to hit remove and now that clip
does not have the eq added onto it these
tools definitely work best in bulk when
you are selecting multiple clips and
adding and subtracting attributes from
them now for this next one i use this
every single time i edit a youtube video
when i'm ready to start editing the
audio i go up here and before i actually
start messing with the eq i put the clip
that i want to edit on a loop all you
have to do is hit the forward slash and
if your playback is set to loop which
you can change that in your settings
then it is going to loop once it reaches
the end of the clip every time you color
grid you really should be looking at
your scope so hitting command 7 is going
to pull that up and then hitting command
7 again is going to get rid of it when
trimming a clip you could hit b and then
hit a again select the clip you want to
delete and that is going to trim it off
but there's actually a faster way to do
it if you know this is the end of your
clip and you want the rest of it to be
gone you can hit option close bracket
and that is going to automatically
delete the rest of the clip for you
holding down option and hitting open
bracket is going to do the same thing on
the other end trimming the beginning of
the clip if you temporarily want to
disable something on your edit you can
hit v and that will remove it without
deleting it and you can do the same
thing with an audio file so you can
watch it back without the audio without
deleting your audio and then hitting v
again is going to bring those assets
right back if you want to just listen to
an audio track instead of disabling all
the sound effects and audio in the video
what you can do is select the video or
audio track that you want to listen to
and hit option s on your keyboard and
option s to bring it back and you can do
this with multiple clips so if we want
to select both of these clips and hit
option s that is going to disable
everything else and solo out just these
tracks so we can listen to these only
have you ever done something you did not
want to do and you wanted to go back
like delete your entire project well you
just have to hit command z and that is
going to bring it right back now if you
want to redo what you did instead of
undoing you can hit shift command z and
that is going to redo what you just did
now since we're on the track of saving
time i actually have a few more tips for
you guys that are not keyboard shortcuts
but these are going to help you save so
much time because getting started when
video editing when it takes a long time
and it's a slow process it's just not as
fun we want to be able to do it quickly
and get our videos out as quick as
possible so here are some ways to save
some time editing tip number one is to
use proxies nolan what is a proxy
good question a proxy is a lower quality
version of your actual video so you can
edit with this lower quality version
your computer runs a whole lot faster
you're not going to run into drop frame
rates or loading times anything like
that because it's it's lower quality and
then at the very end of editing you
switch out the lower quality with your
good quality and it does all the magic
and it replaces all those files and then
when you export it it looks beautiful it
looks high quality and it's gorgeous and
you save time because you're editing
with the lower quality stuff making your
computer run faster this is how you do
inside of final cut pro x you can see
right here i have my library set up i
got my event and project ready to go i'm
solid all i need to do is import some
footage i'm gonna right click i'm gonna
hit import media and at this point let
me go to the correct folder right here
in my hide likes and comments folder is
an upcoming video i'm gonna edit for
think media to the right you are going
to see this transcode section this is
where you can actually create the
proxies and i'll show you how this is
stored and all that kind of good stuff
but there are basically two different
things you need to know here you got
optimized media and you have proxy media
optimized media basically says that it's
going to take your sony or canon files
whatever you're shooting with it's going
to turn it into a progress file and that
is going to run smoother inside of final
cut pro 10. now a lot of you guys
probably already had that turned on but
your files are still running so because
it's 4k and you know your computer
probably is not that good well proxy is
going to be better for you if your
computer is older or if your videos are
running slow in your editing software
now under our proxy media we have prores
proxy and we have h.264
honestly you could use either of these
i've tried both of them out and they
both run great on my computer but i like
to use prores proxies because final cut
pro likes to use prores because it's
apple and anyways doesn't matter but i
like to use prores proxy and here you
can choose a frame size now i shoot all
my stuff in 4k 50 is gonna turn that in
to 1080 hd and it actually doesn't even
look too bad i mean of course it is
lower quality but it honestly really
doesn't look that bad i definitely
recommend trying that out and seeing how
your computer runs now if it's still
running a little bit slow you can set it
to a lower resolution like 25 or 12.5
percent 25 for me i've used it before
and it definitely works great 50 works
for me too but 25 is a lower quality and
it's just going to give you faster files
to work with when editing down here you
could also set it to you know 1080 hd
which is the same as 50 but you have
those options down here for me i'm just
going to leave mine at 50 percent you
don't need to have optimized media
selected because we are going to be
using proxies the whole time so from
here all you have to do is hit import
selected and because i have the folder
selected that is going to make proxy
files for everything in the folder nice
and easy i'm going to hit import
selected boom so we are importing and
you're going to see something right up
here if you click on this circle you are
going to get this window and this is
going to tell you what is happening and
it tells you that it's transcoding and
analysis remember we are transcoding
some of our footage right now so if i
bring this down you can see there's
three clips that it is turning into
proxy files so we're gonna give this a
few minutes we're gonna take a sip of
water and uh come back to it when it's
ready to go
am i the only one who uses a gigantic
water bottle
100. okay sweet so we're all done and we
can exit out of this our proxy files are
now made before i show you how to
actually use these in final cut pro x
let me show you where they are stored so
inside the folder where i actually
uploaded all that footage it was two
video files and one audio file we have
an optimized media and proxy media now
this kind of confuses me because i
didn't select optimize media but in here
we have the it looks like it is the
audio but for some reason it's a mov but
it's the audio file anyway so there's
that but then in our proxy which is what
we're going to be using we have our
video files i couldn't get that word out
so right here if i open this up we can
see that it doesn't even look that bad
honestly but this is our proxy file and
then we have our screen share and you
can see this definitely does look a bit
lower quality than what it actually was
okay this is how you use them now in
final cut pro 10 for people wondering
where they're stored that is exactly
where they're stored nice and easy okay
moving on so let's go ahead and just
throw my entire video down into this
timeline so i can show you guys how to
use this so we got our video right here
and basically all you need to do is go
to this upper right hand corner where it
says view and change this from optimized
original to proxy now proxy only or
proxy preferred here's the difference
proxy only will only show you proxies so
if you have something in there that was
not proxied if i add in a new video that
maybe i didn't make into a proxy file
it's not going to show that's why i like
to use proxy preferred because then it
can mix in the two and it's using
proxies if it has it so i'm just going
to select proxy preferred and now this
video in my timeline is the proxy now
before going out to actually share and
export the video you want to make sure
you change this back to optimized
original it's okay if you forget because
uh final cut pro actually let you know
we'll say hey do you want to export your
proxies and you're going to say no and
then you're going to go back you're
going to change it and then re-export it
so don't worry about that but that's how
you do it and that is going to speed up
your workflow a ton especially if you
have an older laptop an older computer
definitely start using proxies i hate
the the spinning wheel of death the drop
frames all that stuff it slows it down
we're trying to save time number two i'm
gonna call speedy rough cut okay we are
going to speed through and fly through
this uh 11 minute and 24 second clip and
trim it down by this little editing
workflow thing that i do
let me show you so i filmed the video in
one long clip and i need to trim it down
into all the good parts and i'm going to
show you exactly how i do this for every
single video and i swear it saves me so
much time now if you are going through
and you're starting at the beginning and
you're just hitting play
and you're watching this like this is
boring you don't want to watch this we
can skip through all of this and save a
bunch of time the main thing that you
want to look for here is the audio
waveforms we are going to be editing
while looking at the audio waveforms and
that is these little waveforms down here
we are going to be using these right
here you can see there are no waveforms
which means it's silent which means i'm
not talking and therefore we can go
ahead and just cut that out to start
with okay so that's that that's kind of
the idea but we're gonna get deeper and
i'm gonna show you how you can really
start to save time by using these
waveforms now because i shot this video
i already know that this beginning part
really is nothing because i kind of mess
with the background and then i come back
over and i start right around this point
so i'm going to go ahead and just chop
all this off and i'm going to show you
how to do this right now so officially
right here is when i start uh the video
and i start trying to talk to it now
instead of hitting play and listening to
my entire take what i do is i hit play i
listen to the first like three four five
words and then i move it to the next
audio waveform and then i move to the
next one and the next one because what
happens when i shoot videos like this is
i often mess up and then i'll redo what
i was trying to say and when i move on
to my next sentence i know that my last
take was my best take and so that's how
i get my rough cut let me actually just
show you exactly how i do this now in
order to disable
now in order to turn off
now in order to turn off your
in order to hide your now in order to
hide your your dislikes and your likes
and forget to hide your dislikes and
you're like
what i like to do okay i moved on
because what i was saying is in order to
disable in order to turn off whatever
right
right here it was uh the last time that
i said that when i jumped forward to
this next waveform i was talking about
something different so i know for sure
that this is at least probably my last
take i know that this was the same thing
but i'm going to go ahead and delete all
of that and now i'm going to listen to
this again it looks like there might be
some pauses right in this area maybe in
this area i can't tell if i just talked
slower there or if that's an actual
pause but i'm going to go ahead and
listen to that right now
now in order to hide your dis
videos first thing one
you want to make sure
once you have done
studio okay so i know that's all good
because i kept talking i never stopped
and so i'm going to go ahead and hit b
on my keyboard and select right there
because i know that's the end of the
clip and i'm going to do the same thing
again so you can see here that i'm
really trying to figure out what i want
to say this is probably the hook in the
video and so i'm going to fast forward
because look all of this is just nothing
i'm kind of probably writing something
out i'm thinking about what i'm going to
say i'm going to do it again right here
all right here we go
now i'm going to show you now i'm going
to show you right now i'm going to show
you how to do this on a video
you can also do this
all right so this right here this is it
i'm going to delete all of this
and keep going i'm going to show you how
this when you are uploading this that
way you never every time you can just do
let's say you want to and you can also
you can all you can also do this on
now if you wanted to do this
on all your videos you
also do this on multiple videos so i'm
actually saying the same thing here so i
know that i redid it i just changed the
wording a little bit and also here's
another thing i can see that i talked
for a long time right here which makes
me think that this is probably my best
take so i'm going to go ahead and delete
that because i already know that i redid
it and uh but let me hear it because i
might have redone it i don't remember
but that's why you just listened to the
first little bit you don't have to
listen to all of it you can do that in
the next step so that's basically how i
go through the first cut on every single
think media video i look at the
waveforms i listen to the first couple
words and then i figure out which was my
last take which was my best take and i
move on from there so now that i have a
rough cut in order to just go ahead and
watch it through maybe i want to cut
some pieces out instead of playing it
back at 100 and just watching it at 100
what i'm gonna do is i'm hit the
spacebar and then i'm going to hit the
letter l now this is going to work on
any editing software and this is going
to speed up your playback so that you
can listen and watch it at a faster time
than 100
which is awesome because you don't need
to watch the whole thing back at 100
especially when it's just a rough cut
and you're editing it uh to trim down
the fat and all that kind of stuff so
i'm going to hit the space button then
i'm going to hit l to speed it up now in
order to hide your disc
on youtube as well as turn off the
comments on your videos first you want
to do is log into your youtube account
now i use this all the time sometimes i
have 20 minute long tutorials on here
that i'm watching back and just by
hitting that l button to watch it back
i'm saving myself like five minutes okay
every time i watch it all the way
through and that really adds up over
time as you are editing your project
inside your editing software tip number
four is to copy and paste attributes
most of us know that you can hit command
c and then command v to copy and paste a
clip to another clip but what happens is
that this pastes everything onto the
next clip that includes any audio
effects any cropping any sort of luts
that you put on is going to paste
everything well in order just to copy
and paste a few things that you want to
move on whether it's just some audio
effects or maybe a color grade or maybe
a crop you can do that all you need to
do is select your clip we are going to
hit command c and there are a few things
different on this clip than the rest of
the clips but let's say i want to paste
that the color grade only i don't want
to paste the crop you can see i have a
crop here crops back out i just want to
paste the color grade what you want to
do is hit shift command v and this is
going to pull up your paste attributes
now this is really cool because you can
select and deselect things that you do
not want to paste over so like i said i
do not want my crop so i'm going to go
ahead and just unselect that and i
changed the volume i do not want to
adjust the volume on this next clip and
now all i'm pasting over is this custom
lut so i'll hit paste and you can see it
has not affected the audio it has not
affected the crop it's just sent over my
lut i use this all the time especially
for audio because usually i have a grade
done and then i'll do my audio editing
last and i copy just the audio maybe the
volume and some eq and stuff like that
i'll copy it and paste it to all the
clips and it's not going to affect any
of my crop ins crop outs or handheld
shakes or anything that i do like that
it's only going to paste over my audio
effects same with luts and different
effects like that if you are adding on
effects whether it be a crop or a lut
onto every single clip that you want
that's going to be a waste of time
select all of them and just do paste
attributes select what you want it to be
it saved me a whole lot of time so now
you know tip number five is to create
presets this saves you so much time
because instead of eq'ing the same mic
over and over again you can actually
create say an eq like this for this usb
mic and then i can use that every single
time i use this mic it's a preset it's
built out i can click one button and
it's gonna do the rest for me this works
with video effects this works with color
grading you can actually save a lot
maybe with some tweaks that you've made
to it and then save this as a preset
that way when you add in the lut it's
also gonna add in those little tweaks
that you've made to kind of make it your
own and fit your camera best here's how
you do it first let's start with an
audio preset so you can see here that
i've made some adjustments to the eq on
this microphone i can exit out of this
you can see that is the only thing i've
done here let's say i want the db to be
zero okay perfect now to save this as a
preset all you have to do is go down
here hit save effects preset from here
you can select what you want to save so
i'm just going to call this samson q2u
because that is the microphone that i am
using you're also going to see other
options if you add in some sort of like
reverb or noise reduction you're going
to have those options here you can
select them but for me all i've done is
some eq and volume which is fine and i
and you definitely want to make sure
that stretch to fit is selected that way
it takes whatever clip and it stretches
it out to the full thing so that your
effect is saved to your entire clip from
here all you got to do is hit save now
what you can do is go over to your
effects you can scroll down to audio and
you can see that you have custom and
here are some of my custom ones so i'm
going to use the samsung qtu that i just
made and i'm going to drag it over this
clip right here now you can see that it
has added in my eq to be exactly like
the other one this is great if you use
the same mic for your youtube videos you
definitely want to be saving presets
because instead of eq'ing the same mic
in the same room every time you don't
need to do that just create a preset and
drag and drop and you're gonna be set to
go you can do the same thing with video
so you can see i have a lut here and
then i have some color wheels where i
just change some like contrast stuff
like that but if i want to save this as
a preset both of these together i can go
to save effects preset now here i do
want my custom lot my color wheels but i
do not want my crop and stretch to fit
is fine i can go ahead and rename this
to the a7s3 which is the camera that i'm
using for this shot now something here
and this is the same with audio but the
audio one was correct here it's set to
the category 360. i actually don't want
to save it to 360. i'll save it to a new
category and we can call it custom you
can really call it whatever you want but
i'll just go ahead and call it custom as
well you'll hit create and from there
it's going to save to a brand new
category called custom so now over here
in the effects if we go to custom you
are going to see my a7 s3 preset we can
scroll over something that has no color
on it and boom drag and drop and you're
good to go so now you know the basics of
editing your videos and you know how to
speed up that workflow so you can be
more of a professional editor but let's
get into some of the fun stuff that you
can do inside of the software because
there is a whole lot you can do inside
of final cut and there's a lot of cool
effects that you can do inside of final
cut pro so these are going to be 10
effects that a lot of youtubers use in
their videos that you can do in yours
too and this is for beginners i'm gonna
walk you through step by step exactly
how to do this so check out these 10
effects now number one is to use text
pop-ups this is really popular when it
comes to youtubers and it's pretty
simple inside of final cut pro 10. let
me show you exactly what i'm talking
about and then i will show you how to do
it now let's get right into this video
because we have a lot to talk about
yeah cheesy jokes
welcome to the youtube channel so as you
saw here this text was popping up now
i'm going to delete this and start from
scratch to show you guys exactly how to
do this first things first you want to
go into your text and i'm just going to
go ahead and use a custom one right here
i'm going to drag this over i'm kind of
going to resize this so that you know
it's as long as what i am saying because
i'm gonna have them pop up right as i
say the word it's gonna pop up you have
a lot to talk about
and it's gonna end right about there so
now that that's all set i'm gonna go
ahead and put in my text now that i have
my text on the screen it's pretty simple
what i like to do first is actually get
in here and just cut them up to the
words now this doesn't have to be
perfect because it's actually really
easy to retime these so that it pops up
at exactly when you want to but what i
like to do is just really quickly go
through and cut these up into the
different words okay that's not perfect
but you know somewhere around here now
you can see that i've cut up the titles
what i'm going to do now is start over
here on number one and i am going to go
to crop and then change this to trim so
if it's on crop you don't want that you
want to change this to trim from here
all you have to do is take this right
side of the box and start to drag it
over trimming off every single word
except for your first word now what we
could do is go over click this again go
to trim and go ahead and do the exact
same thing we just did leaving our
second word and our first word
visible now now we could just do this
for every single text but to speed up
your workflow a little bit you could do
a copy and paste all you got to do is
select one that you've already trimmed
you're going to hit command c go to your
next one and then you're going to hit
command option v from there it's going
to chop off most of the words and you
just have to drag it to your next word
so i'm gonna go ahead and do this with
the rest of them and it really doesn't
take that long and you get yourself a
really cool effect by the end of it
obviously on your last one here you want
to leave all the words visible and now
we can go through we can watch it and
see if we need to kind of retime any of
the words
we have a lot to talk about
so i can maybe move this second to last
word latte talk about we have a lot to
talk about
now that's looking pretty good and it's
as easy as that just using the trim tool
you also could use the mask tool but i
found for stuff like this using the trim
tool has found to be easier for me next
up i'm going to show you guys how to
blur out a piece of the image whether
you want to censor it or hide it you can
definitely do that inside of final cut
pro x i've done this before for clients
where they needed to actually blur out a
brand or something in the background
like an address and so i've had to use
this before but i'll show you how to do
that right now so first off we have our
clip right here and for this case i'm
just gonna blur out my coffee cup
because it's moving and i'll show you
guys how to kind of move that around as
well so the first step you actually want
to do is to copy and paste the clip that
you are going to blur and put one on top
of the other so i'm going to go ahead
and move this right on top of there now
we have two different clips now the top
one is going to be our blur and we're
going to use a mask to control what we
want to blur so let's start with our
effects and actually going to pick out a
blur there's two that i like to use one
is just kind of your classic out of
focus blur and the second one is more of
a pixelated blur so i'll show you where
both of those are if you go over here to
blur you can see right here that if i
throw this on top everything is out of
focus it's a pretty nice blur this is
kind of something that you would see on
tv however i'd like to use the pixelate
blur because it's just kind of fun and
funny and so i like to use that
sometimes if we click on all and we go
to search for pixel we'll see a pixelate
right here and if we throw that on top
you are going to see that it does this
whole pixelating effect and you can
really choose how much you want to do
that let's get the copy up here and
maybe we want to make it even more
blurry now that we have done our blur
what we want to do next is pick our mask
so i'm going to search for mask make
sure you're dragging this on the top
layer of your video and from here you
can start to draw a mask around exactly
what you want to blur out and we'll just
go ahead and blur out this entire coffee
cup now from here it doesn't look too
good but you can start to mess around so
that it fits around whatever it is that
you're blowing out a bit better and then
we want to use the feather tool this is
going to make it look a whole lot
smoother you can even drag this past 100
if you would like and so you know this
is looking fine for me as far as a blur
goes i think it looks great now you can
see the issue here is that the coffee
cup kind of comes into the blower and it
also goes out of the blur so what i'm
going to show you how to do is how to
move this blur effect over neat
overnight over top of a moving object so
i'm going to move it to the first frame
that it comes into which is right here
and i'm just going to drag this entire
masking tool with the blur effect over
that mug so that's right there i'm going
to go ahead and start my keyframes
underneath your mask you want to open up
your transforms and then you're going to
click this keyframe button right here on
position and i like to go about three or
four frames and move the mask if i'm
moving it really fast maybe i would do
less every frame or every other frame
but for something like this you can
really get away with three four frames
so i'm gonna start here and i'm just
going to move forward three frames now
that i move forward three frames i'm
going to move my mask back up move
forward three frames again
continue to move my mask
and i'm to do this for the entire clip
now that i'm done you can see that the
mask is actually starting on the clip
and i don't want it to start on the clip
so to go to my first keyframe i'm going
to hit this button right here and then
i'm gonna go back a few frames and move
this all the way out so as we go forward
now it's going to come up with the mug
which is perfect so let's hit play and
see what this looks like
awesome so the blur is moving around
with the mug and it looks great and
blurred and the nice thing about this is
now that we've done a mask that's moving
we can actually replace this effect with
anything so if we wanted to change this
to our other blur it's really easy as
just dragging this on top of the clip
and deleting the pixelate button now we
want to move this back up top right
where the pixelate was and from here you
can mess with the amount of blur you can
make a more blurry less blurry and
you're going to see that the same effect
happens all the movement have been kept
the same but now it's just a different
type of blur next up i'm going to show
you guys a little stop motion effect i
use this on my wife's channel where her
name pops up and i kind of made this
stop-motion effect with her name and i
did that all manually inside of final
cut pro 10 so i'm gonna show you exactly
how i did that so right here i did a
little text that says hello everybody
and i'm gonna show you kind of what this
effect looks like just kind of bounces
back and forth kind of like a stop
motion vibe so it's really easy to do
this what i'm going to do is actually
delete all of this but keep one of my
text so first of all you want to start
with what it could be a picture it could
be text it really could be whatever you
want it to be to kind of do this effect
and so all of it is going to be the same
whether it's text a picture graphic
whatever so the trick here is to make
your text three frames long and then
we're gonna go from there so let's start
by doing that one two three i'm gonna go
ahead hit b which is the blade tool i'm
going to chop that off now i have this
text that is three frames long and what
you want to do is hit command c command
v and you're going to paste it this next
one what you want to do is go to your
transform tool and you want to adjust it
just a little bit you don't want to do
it a lot but you just want to change it
slightly you're then going to copy and
paste that one right after it and you're
going to do the same thing you're just
going to adjust the rotation a little
bit maybe even the positioning a little
bit command c
command v and do the same thing again
make sure that it's not too crazy all
over the place or it might be a bit too
much but you guys will get the hang of
this and then once you have about six to
ten of these you're just going to
command copy all of them and paste those
over and over again so i'll just do a
couple more here adjusting it just
slightly so that they look a little bit
different giving that stop motion effect
all right now that i have done seven of
them i'm gonna go ahead and hit play and
see how it looks
i think it looks pretty good and once
you're happy with how it looks all you
have to do is copy and paste that over
and over again to make it as long as you
want so i hit command c to copy i'll hit
command v and then command v again again
again as long as i want it to last and
once you have it as long as you want you
have a really cool stop motion effect to
your youtube videos next up i'm going to
show you guys how to add overlays to
make your shot a bit more interesting so
when i first started using this i was
actually adding some muzzle flashes to
some guns for these little action films
that i was shooting with my friends but
really this works for anything if you
want to do light leaks or any sort of
glitches stuff like that this works
really well it basically just takes the
black in a background image or a video
and it makes it transparent so when you
overlay that onto your video it's going
to be transparent and the black will go
away and everything else is going to be
on top of your image so right here you
can see that the video is pretty bland
so i'm going to add some overlays just
to spice things up a little bit right
here i have this glitch overlay which i
think i just got off of youtube but it
kind of has these numbers kind of techy
uh computer things going on and so to
get rid of the black so that it shows
through all you have to do is select the
video come up here to blend mode and
you're going to change that to screen
once you've done that you see that you
get these textures coming through and
there is no more black screen everything
is transparent and it kind of adds to
this cool computer shot going on so i'm
gonna do the same exact thing with this
glitch effect right here which we
actually got off of story blocks and so
i'm gonna go to blend mode change that
again to screen and this is gonna add a
cool little transition to my next shot
and so let me show you what this looks
like now
i think it's really cool it adds a lot
to the shot and again you can get
creative with this and add tons of stuff
to your footage to make it look cooler
again those light leaks i've used a lot
of times different glitch effects stuff
like that you can add on top of your
video by using the screen blend mode i'm
gonna show you guys how to do this
effect where it shows you the before and
after so if you're redoing a room or if
you're doing like a color grade like i
am doing here you can actually do a
sliding effect to show the before versus
the after now right here i have an
adjustment layer and a clip and this
adjustment layer is just adding in my
color to my shot so you can see this is
what it looks like completely flat and
then you have your adjustment layer now
with this effect you actually can't use
an adjustment layer and i'll show you
why later so what i want to do is i want
to copy this i'm going to delete my
adjustment layer and i'm just going to
paste that onto my actual video now in
order for this effect to work you do
need two clips so i'm going to copy this
exact clip and paste this now this would
work exactly if it was your before shot
and your after shot but for me i'm going
to do before my color grade and after my
color grade so the top one is going to
be the after shot and the before is
going to be the bottom so what i'm going
to do is delete everything on this
bottom clip to make it flat again and
you can see here if i mute this video
feed on top our bottom layer is the
before our top layer is the after from
here you're going to go into the
transitions and you're going to go to
the search and look up wipe and then you
are going to drag the wipe transition
onto the top layer you can actually
delete this end one and then you want to
extend this to make it a lot longer and
i'll show you guys what this looks like
now so right now you can't even see the
top layer you just see the before shot
which is down here and then as it plays
through you are going to see this wipe
effect where it shows you the color
grade that i've done you can adjust the
duration of the white by dragging it
left and right to make it longer or
shorter you can also click on this
transition and if you go up here you're
going to see that you have a few
different options so if you want to go
from left to right you can also do that
so now it is dragging from the left side
to the right side you can also change
the edge treatment i usually like to
leave this on feather where it just kind
of blends in the two videos but you also
could do like a solid color like this
and make it white or black and you can
make the border color a lot smaller and
then that way it's kind of showing you
the before after using a line of color
to distinguish the two now i don't know
about you but have you ever accidentally
gotten like a shotgun microphone in your
shot or a light in your shot like you
can see up here i have this light up
there it was not supposed to be in my
shot but it was but luckily in final cut
pro there is a fix that you can do for
this what you want to do is copy and
paste the clip that you are going to
cover and so we are going to cover up
this light right here so what i'm going
to do here is take this color right
around here because it's going to be you
know about the same color i'm just going
to drag that over the light and then
feather it out so that no one can tell
in our effects we're going to be looking
for the mask tool and we can just draw a
simple mask i'm going to drag that on
top now from here i just want to take
this color you know about the same size
of the light and then close that off so
now that we've done that we are going to
take the feather option and put that to
a hundred and then on our transform or
you can go to this right here we are
going to drag this up above now if i
completely remove the bottom layer
you're going to see what's happening
here i'm taking this color that i just
got with the mask and then i'm actually
going to feather this out a bit more so
that it's much smoother and all you have
to do is make sure that it's completely
covering up that light or the microphone
whatever it is you want to hide in the
shot you can do this simply by adding in
a mask and dragging something over top
of it and then by adding in some
feathering you're really going to smooth
out this shot so it looks nice and clean
and now it looks like there was no light
ever there so i can click this on and
off you can see that's before and this
is after another really cool easy trick
that i use for our think media videos is
ken burns so you can see here that we
have a few different b-roll shots and
they're just pretty simple right they're
not too exciting they're pretty boring
there's not a lot of camera movement
happening so what i'm going to do here
is let me trim this one first but what
i'm going to do here is add in some ken
burns and this is going to emulate a
camera movement so all you got to do is
click this arrow right here we're going
to go to crop and down here you're going
to hit ken burns now here you have a
start option and the n option so you can
see it starts completely wide and then
it zooms in ending a bit closer i'll
show you what this looks like
now it looks like there is a zoom
happening and so we're going to do the
same thing with this next shot but i'm
going to show you a few more things that
you can do with this so here we can see
that now it's doing a zoom out where
it's starting in tight and then it is
coming and zooming out showing us the
entire shot but if you want to switch
that around so it's also zooming in all
you have to do is hit these little
arrows right here and that is going to
swap these for you so it's also going to
do another zoom in for you and if we
actually want to just switch that back
it's as simple as moving that now if you
want to make it really drastic and zoom
in a bunch you can move these around as
much as you want i don't like to make it
super obvious i like to do kind of a
subtle zoom in or zoom out effect but
whatever floats your boat you can
definitely do and mess around with these
as well after adding in those ken burns
you can see that this movement to the
shot really just adds a lot to these
b-roll clips and gives it a bit more
spice and i definitely think it's
something worth messing with because it
can really take your shot to the next
level just adding that little bit of
camera movement really can make a big
difference for this next effect we use
this all the time at think media this is
when our text swooshes in and swooshes
out and we add in the sound effects i'm
going to show you how we do that so
right here you see that i have my name i
have my instagram handle all you got to
do is go to your transitions and look
for slide this is the transition that i
use you can drag this right over your
image or your text and then you want to
click on this transition and come up
here and this is where you mess with the
settings so we have slide in which is
exactly what i want and then at the end
it's going to slide out and the
direction i want to go is right so
that's perfect that's kind of the preset
that it's set to but you'll see here
when it goes to the other clip
that's not what i want happening so
something wrong is here so i'm going to
click on this transition and we are
going to go back up here we can see that
it's set to slide in i don't want it to
slide in i want it to slide out and for
the direction i want it to slide to the
left so it goes back that way now if we
watch again
slides in
slides out that's perfect now from here
all we have to do to make the null
multex do the same exact thing is hit
copy and paste onto this one now it's
not going to paste both transitions you
need to go back up here you need to hit
command c click down here hit command v
now it has perfectly copy and pasted
every transition onto both of them so
when we hit play
they both come in at the same exact time
they both go out at the same exact time
if you want to make these quicker or
longer you can drag this to the left to
make it quicker you can also drag it to
the right to make it last longer be a
longer slide and then you would just
match these up so that they match and
this is just going to come in a bit
slower the next effect i want to show
you guys is the handheld effect so we're
going to search for a handheld and drag
this over our clip and this is going to
give our static tripod shot a handheld
look so once we hit play we're going to
see that it looks like someone is
holding the camera they're a little bit
shaky but we can mess with those
settings by clicking on our video and up
here and effects we can mess with the
shakiness and the distance if we want to
make it more shaky we can drag it to the
right if we want to make it less shaky
we can drag to the left i like to keep
my shakiness around 15 to 10 and then my
distance i like to bring back down about
to 10 to 15 as well and we can see what
this looks like now with those settings
it's definitely a lot less shaky this is
a bit more of my taste and i like to
throw this in on videos to just spice
things up and get people on their toes
because when they're seeing the same
shot over and over again they can start
to tune it out so cropping in cropping
out adding in these handheld effects
this is great for resetting the viewers
attention to get them to watch longer
little stuff like this does wonders and
i think it's a really cool effect that
you can add to your videos i know i got
a lot of questions on that in a previous
video so for those of you asking that is
exactly how i do it now i've actually
had a lot of people ask me about this
effect that i'm going to show you guys
as well and this is when the camera
tracks on my face so as i move my face
around the camera tracks with me let me
show you exactly how i do it and i use
keyframes to do it but there's a trick
here that makes it a whole lot easier so
i'm going to drag this custom text onto
my video and then i'm just going to add
in the letter x it really could be
anything it could be a dot let's just do
a dot and i'm going to drag this right
into the middle of my eyes now this
looks really weird at the moment but i
promise you guys it's going to be a
really cool effect so on this clip right
now we have scaled the image so that it
is a bit closer and you can see that as
i hit play
i move my head around like this and i'm
just going to do a little camera track
on my face now the reason i put the dot
right there is because for these
keyframes i want to make sure that my
middle of my face stays in the center of
the frame the entire time that is what's
gonna make this look really interesting
look really cool and the camera kind of
move with my head as i move it around so
now that i have the video selected i'm
going to add a keyframe and i'm just
gonna go frame by frame moving this
image around to stay on track with this
little dot in the center of the screen
for something like this i'll go forward
every two frames or if there's a lot of
movement i'll just do it frame by frame
but for something like this i could
probably get away by jumping for two
frames adding a keyframe jump forward
two frames again and adding a new
keyframe and for those of you asking if
you're brand new once you move something
around it automatically adds in a
keyframe for you so all you got to do is
start your keyframes once and then we
can jump forward two frames once you
move it like this you can see that this
has a check mark if i jump forward two
more frames you can see that it is not
selected yet there is no keyframe but as
i move this around it adds in a keyframe
for me jump forward two frames and just
do this throughout the entire thing
all right now before we watch this we
want to get rid of this dot so i'll
delete that and then i'm going to hit
the play button
all right so that's pretty cool so you
can see as you're talking you know it
crops in and it does this funny little
tracking on the face effect again people
ask me about that one that's exactly how
i do it moving on to color grading no
matter what camera you have color
grading can really level up your camera
make it look nicer by adding some
saturation or contrast to your shot i'm
going to share what you need to know
about color correction and color grading
for the beginner so without further ado
here it is now there is a difference
between color grading and color
correction most people just call it
color grading which is totally fine but
we're going to cover both of those in
this video and show you how to do that
to your footage color grading basically
is adding a stylistic look to your
footage to make it look cinematic or
vibrant something like that whereas
color correction is kind of fixing the
white balance fixing the exposure the
contrast stuff like that so we're going
to cover both of those things in this
video so let's get right into it now the
very first thing you want to do inside a
final cut pro x is make sure that your
proxies are not on if you go to this
view tab right here we can see that if
we had proxy preferred or proxy only
then we would want to change that to
optimized original so make sure you just
hit optimized original and that is going
to bring up your original files which is
going to be best for color grading you
don't want to color grade or color
correct your proxy files you want to
make sure you have those original files
to color grade with that selected i like
to go to the next step and i like to
open up my scopes kind of get everything
ready for color grading and i'll show
you what those scopes are if you go up
to the view tab you are going to see
video scopes right here you can also hit
command 7 to bring those up and if we
click that we're going to see these uh
colors the red the green the blue and
we're going to change all this but these
things are going to make it a lot easier
for us to color grade and i'll show you
how to use this but instead of doing
this i actually like to change up my
workspace just a little bit so that
these are as big as possible and the
easiest way to do this is if you go up
here to window you will see workspaces
and right here there's color and effects
if you pull this up you are going to see
this entire left side just go away and
this is going to make everything nice
and big for you perfect for color
grading and color correcting so this is
a very nice workspace that you can use
if you are color grading and if you want
to change that back maybe you're ready
to go back
to the edit what you can do is go up to
window hover over workspaces and you can
go back to default and this is going to
put it back just how you had it so going
back to my workspaces going to color and
effects i actually don't need all four
of these so what i like to do is go up
here to view and then i'm gonna change
this just to two one on top one on
bottom now this is looking great and if
you want to use it like this which is
how i use it you can go back up to
window you can go to workspaces you can
actually save this workspace we'll just
call it color grading which i already
have mine saved as color grading but if
you hit save this is going to save this
workspace for you so that you don't have
to go in and mess with this every time
you just go to window workspace now when
you hit color grading it is going to
pull this up how you like it now if
you're a beginner and you're just
learning how to color grade the odds are
you don't really have a flat log image
which would look something like this
right here this is a flat image or what
they would call a log image the odds are
you're shooting some videos on your
standard picture profile on your camera
now that's totally fine you can still
mess with these colors and i'm gonna
show you how to do that that's why i
have some footage here where it's a bit
colored already this is just the
standard picture profile on the sony zv1
and i have some different clips here
that we're going to look at this one
right here with my face in it show you
how to kind of color when there are some
skin tones in there as well as just some
random shots here with a lot of
different greens and blues different
colors to mess around with now something
you want to get familiar with is your
color inspector what you can do is hit
the color board right here and if you
drag this onto your clip in this
inspector right here you are going to
see a color board and you can open that
up and from here you can make some
adjustments but i actually do not like
to use the color board now instead of
doing that this is actually a shortcut
as well you can just click on this
little color inspector triangle right
here and this is going to pull up uh the
same thing for you but this is actually
called the color wheels now odds are if
you click on that it's gonna pull up
your color board to change that just go
into final cut pro go to preferences and
right here under general we can see
color correction and it's going to be
set onto color board just naturally but
we want to set this to color wheels with
that selected we can exit out of that
now you can see when you click on this
triangle it's just going to pull up your
color wheels right here let's start by
taking a look at these four wheels and
what they do and how they can affect
your image this top wheel right here is
our master wheel so this is going to
affect everything we have shadows mid
tones and highlights but the master is
going to affect all of those all three
shadow midtones and highlights now the
left side of the wheel is our saturation
you can see it's a bit more blue up here
and it's a bit more faded out down here
that lets you know that it is the
saturation so as we go up this is going
to make things a lot more saturated you
can see how much more vibrant this image
is and if i bring it all the way down
you can see that it's going to turn to
black and white there is no saturation
to these colors now each wheel kind of
has the same layout on the left side you
are going to have that saturation so
let's go to shadows and if i pull those
all the way down you're gonna see that
the shadows are now black and white but
we still have some mid-tones and
highlights a lot of these blues still
have some color now back up here on
master the right side of the wheel is
going to be our exposure you can see up
here it's a bit brighter down here it's
darker so as we increase the master it's
going to make everything much brighter
starting to blow out some of our image
doesn't look the best but as we darken
it this is going to darken our entire
image make everything a lot darker now
right here in the center we can actually
move this little point around and this
is going to add color into our entire
shot so if i drag this up into the
magenta it's going to make everything a
bit more magenta i can do the same if i
want to pull that into the green or i
want to make it warmer make it a bit
orange you can do that by dragging these
around in each of these wheels now real
quick i'm just going to throw these all
around i'm going to show you how to
reset these if you ever need to so let's
say you want to reset all of it all you
have to do is click on this little reset
button and that is going to bring
everything back to normal for this one
wheel but let's say you don't want to
bring everything back you just want to
bring back maybe this piece right here
if you double click that is going to
bring back just that property i can do
the same with the saturation by double
clicking it's going to bring it back
double clicking gonna bring it back so
that's how you can kind of reset some of
these values as you are going through
your color grade like i mentioned these
are gonna work the same as the master
however this is only going to affect
your shadows this is only going to
affect your highlights this is only
going to affect your mid tones and so
you can mess with each of these by only
affecting you know a specific part of
your shot after i show you what all of
these do i'm going to walk you through
exactly how i color correct and color
grade a shot so stick with me we're
almost there these are the things that
you need to know before you start color
correcting down here we have temperature
tint and hue now this was shot on auto
white balance on the sony zv1 but if you
mess up your white balance this is where
you could fix some of those issues by
sliding these around so this temperature
if you drag it to the right this number
is going to increase and that is going
to increase the warmth of your shot and
the tint is going to increase in magenta
as you pull it to the right and as you
pull it to the left it is going to add
green to your shot if you pull the
temperature left it's going to be cooler
and adding that blue tone to your shot
messing with the hue is going to adjust
all of your colors and kind of swing
them around on your colors wheel making
it look a bit funky this is not
something that i ever use but maybe if
you're shooting a music video or you
know there might be an instance where
you would use this this is where you can
mess with the hue down here under mix i
usually just leave at 1 but if you want
to dial it back so that it's not at 100
strength it's kind of like the opacity
of this effect you can drag this to the
left and zero you can see that there is
nothing happening and to the right you
can see this is with everything applied
i usually leave this at one and i just
dial everything in exactly how i want it
but that is there if you ever want to
dial it back and forth you can do that
if you also want to see kind of the
before and after what you can do is
uncheck this box and this is going to
disable it and then if you check it
again it's going to bring it back now
that you know what these wheels do let's
actually color correct and color grade
this image to look a bit better a bit
more vibrant maybe a bit more summery
but first we want to take a look at
these scopes over here now these might
be a bit intimidating but i promise you
it's really easy if you just take the
time and understand what these are it's
going to help you so much right now
we're just going to ignore this vector
scope which is this circle up here and
we are gonna kind of save that for our
part two of this video which is gonna be
a bit more advanced where i'm gonna
cover stuff like luts you know film
simulations adjustment layers grading
log images getting correct skin tone
stuff like that is gonna be an advanced
tutorial where i will use the
spectroscope once that part 2 advanced
tutorial comes out make sure you check
that out because you're going to learn
so much more but you definitely need to
watch this video first because this is
going to lay down the foundations of
color correcting and color grading so
that you're not completely lost when it
comes to the advanced tutorial but for
now we're just going to focus on this
waveform down here which is our luma
waveform now if you ever want to change
these you can click on this right here
and change this from luma sometimes i
use the rgb overlay now this waveform
right here is actually showing us the
values in this shot so as i move this
around you're gonna see this also moves
because this is showing us exactly what
is on screen and it's showing us the
brightness of the shot now on this
waveform we have some numbers the main
thing that you want to look at is this
100 number if you go above this line you
are gonna start losing information in
your shot so for example if we go to our
highlights and we boost these highlights
you can see that the entire graph is now
moving up because it's showing us the
brightness of the shot so as i move
these highlights above 100 you are going
to see that the sky is starting to lose
a lot of its color it just is white now
because it is over this 100 line so you
want to try and keep things that you
want to have color things that you want
to be in the shot below that 100 line
this is the same with the shadows as i
start to decrease the shadows we are
going below this zero line and that
means that we are losing color and
details in the shadows it's starting to
take colors and just make them black so
typically you want most your colors to
be above zero and below 100. as i move
these mid-tones you are going to see
that the waveform kind of scrunches
upwards or if i move it down it's
starting to scrunch downwards and i
really use mid-tones for adding contrast
so let's go to this shot right here and
i'm going to color correct and color
gray this a bit exactly how i would do
this for my own video first things first
you want to make sure you have that clip
selected and then we can start making
our adjustments now when looking at the
shot one of the things i want to fix is
how dark it is around my face because
it's a bit too contrasty for me and so
first thing that i would do is go over
to my mid-tones and on this right side
we have that exposure and i'm just going
to increase this to bring some of that
life back into those mid-tones so we can
see what's going on in the shadows now
when i did that you can see that i
actually lifted this entire thing up so
even though i was just messing with the
mid-tones the shadows were a bit
affected as well and i still want
contrast in this shot so what i'll do is
i will take my shadows and i'm going to
bring those down just to the bottom of
this graph to see how this looks so far
that's looking pretty good i'm going to
mess with my highlights see if i want to
bring those down or up but honestly
where they're at is pretty good you know
everything's at the top of this 100 and
so far i'm happy with how this looks if
i click this on and off you can see how
much we really brought back into the
face how much we brought back into the
shot just by adjusting those mid-tones
up and then bringing the shadows back
down to keep the contrast but also bring
life to those shadows when it comes to
adding saturation i like to use the
master wheel so it affects the entire
shot so i'm just going to increase it
just a hair now that i'm liking how this
looks i kind of want to give this a warm
summer vibe and so we're going to mess
with some of the colors add a bit of
warmth into the shot first i'm going to
start with the temperature and just kind
of increase this and see what this looks
like and you can see as i increase the
warmth it gets a bit green as well so
i'm going to grab the tint and i'm going
to bring it this way to add some magenta
back into this shot now the highlights
i'm just going to add some warmth to
this by dragging it towards these
oranges and now my skin is getting a bit
too orange and so what i'll do is i'll
go to my mid-tones i'm going to pull it
in the opposite direction adding a bit
of blue to the midtones i'm also going
to add a little bit of blue into the
shadows and maybe increase my highlights
even more i'm also going to bring my
highlights down just a hair now this is
definitely more of a stylized shot
everything is a bit warmer it looks very
summery very warm so if i click this on
and off you can see the before and after
is pretty crazy right look how dark this
is it looks really cool it looks natural
but when i click this on everything is
much warmer the shadows have been lifted
and i like the warmth that we're getting
in the sky in those greens i think it
looks really awesome when it comes to
color grading there's no correct way to
do it it definitely is just finessing in
the colors messing with it it takes a
while to figure out you know where you
want your colors in the shadows the mid
tones the highlights and so practice
just start messing with shots there is
no wrong way to do this just start
messing around with it see how it looks
and you'll get better over time now i'm
going to show you a really cool trick
that you can do here in final cut but
first let's copy over these effects
command c we're going to paste them onto
this by hitting option command v now we
can see that it copied everything over
but it's not looking too good so i'm
gonna go back into my color wheels and
make a few adjustments to the exposure i
think it looks a little bit flat so
we're gonna add a little more contrast
to the shot
that's looking a bit better i kind of
like having the highlights a bit lower i
think it looks really cool for this shot
okay now that i like how this is looking
looks very warm very cinematic what i'm
going to do is actually add in a new
thing by clicking up this down arrow
right here we're going to add in our hue
saturation curves now in this video
we're just going to take a look at these
top three the huber's tube the hueversat
and the hubris luma i'm going to show
you what these do and how they can
really affect your image if we click
this eyedropper right here on hue vs hue
i can select any color i want and it is
going to show me what color it is right
here and as i drag this up and down it's
actually going to mess with that color
specifically so it's not going to mess
with the hue on all the colors like that
one little hue wheel did this is going
to mess with just that one color so if i
want to make that blue water a bit more
blue i can drag it down like this and
it's going to add in some more blues and
just change the hue of what the pool
originally was i'm also going to do this
with the green so if i click on this
little green right here there's some
different colors in this tree so like
this is going to be a little bit
different than say this green back here
you can see the screen has a lot more
blue in it but i want to mess with these
colors right here so as i drag these
down they can get really bizarre really
blue and you can mess with these and
kind of fine tune exactly the look that
you're going for let's say i'm really
liking this shot but i think the blue in
the pool is just a bit too saturated i
like the color i just want it less
saturated this is what the humor sat is
for so if you click the eyedropper and
then select the pool color from here if
you drag it down you can desaturate the
pool and if you drag it up it is just
going to increase the saturation so i'm
going to keep it right about there and
i'm going to do the same thing with
these trees because the green is a
really cool green i just do not like how
saturated it is
okay now this is looking really cool so
if i turn this off you can see what this
looks like before and then i turn it on
this is what it looks like after so this
is where you can get really creative and
really stylize a look and color grade
using this hue saturation curves is a
really fun tool just to mess around with
the colors and make something that is
really unique now that i really like
this look i'm going to copy and paste
this image onto a new video so so far it
looks pretty good but i'm going to show
you guys actually the main reason why i
use the hue saturation curves and it's
typically with skin tones and kind of
decreasing maybe some of the redness in
the skin or if the skin is just too
saturated bringing that saturation down
just a little bit and i basically use
this in almost every single think media
video and what i do is i go into the
huber saturation use the eye dropper i
select the skin and then this allows me
to really refine that saturation in the
skin tones if i want to bring it down
just a hair i can and usually the
redness you know on my cheeks or my nose
sometimes can just get a little bit too
red when i add in saturation and so i
can click on my cheeks or my nose and
maybe bring you know this area down a
little bit you can see that the lips now
have no color and so i just bring it
back up until i think it has a good
enough saturation but not too much this
is before any of the hue saturation
curves and this is after the hue
saturation curves this is before the
entire image and this is after now in
this next section someone asked me and
they said how can i edit my videos
better and i made a video on five and a
half tips to edit videos better now the
first tip i actually already went over
earlier in this video so you are going
to see the four and a half tips that are
really going to level up your videos
these are things that really can just
take your video to the next level
whether that's on youtube or wherever it
is that you are posting your videos
these are things that are going to help
keep the audience engaged when they are
watching your videos tip number two is
to cover your edits if your video feels
choppy maybe how to stop a lot when
talking to the camera and edit in all
these little pieces piece by piece one
thing you can do is cover your edit to
make it look like you are just talking
to the camera forever and never really
stopping let me show you what i'm
talking about and what not to do now
when a video is choppy just like this
you can tell when i stop talking and
when i start talking again so let me
show you how to fix this and how to hide
these cuts and the first one is to crop
in by cropping in it resets the viewer's
attention and it looks like you just
kept talking but in reality all you did
was crop the image in and then you crop
the image back out and it looks like you
just kept talking even though there was
a few cuts within this take another
thing you can do to hide your cuts is to
insert b-roll footage adding some video
to overlay on your footage is a great
way to hide those cuts so no one really
knows when you stop talking and start
talking again it just sounds like a
fluent conversation tip number three
this one is really really important and
it's to cut it out trim the fat keep the
meat keep the good stuff get rid of
everything else you want your video to
be as long as it needs to be but as
short as possible now if you're a new
editor you're probably asking well how
do i know what to cut out i feel like i
need all of this stuff in there when in
reality i promise you you can cut things
out the first mindset shift is to watch
it as a viewer watch it as if you're
watching someone else's video now a
really cool hack you can do here is
actually bring someone else into the
room to watch your edit now you're gonna
watch it with them and what you'll
notice is when they're watching it
you're gonna be a lot more critical of
your own work and you're gonna know when
they're getting tired and bored of
watching your video and you're gonna be
like yeah that's not the best i can cut
that out tip number four is to use sound
effects adding some sound effects to
your videos for transitions or when
stuff pops up on the screen or when text
comes on the screen just like this is a
great way to level up your production
value this also helps keep the viewers
engaged helping them watch longer and in
return helping the youtube algorithm
pick up your video so you get more views
this fit tip is really the most
important tip and it's the one thing
that i would tell anyone if they said
give me one tip on editing to level up i
would tell them this but before we get
to that like this video and then comment
down below what other questions do you
have about youtube content creation that
i can help you with let me know down
below okay now the fifth tip is pacing
is everything once someone clicks on
your video the most important thing that
you can do is keep them there you want
to keep the audience retention and one
of the main things to do this is by your
pacing if your video starts off very
slow odds are people are going to click
out and bounce on to the next video
starting off with the right pacing is
great but you want to keep that going
throughout the video so people keep
watching to the very end so let me give
you one practical way on how you can do
this change up the music changing the
music in the middle of a video is a
great way for the viewer to know
whatever just happened is over and we're
on to something new there's a sad moment
in your video where
things aren't going right and just
everything's sad you know using that sad
music can really bring the viewer in to
what you're feeling and this is great
for pacing and then change the music
because i'm not sad anymore the video is
moving on and people are now engaged in
what's next changing your music needs to
happen at the right moment so if there's
something new happening this is a great
time to change the music if there is
drama or something exciting these are
all great chances to change the music
and start new now i actually have
another half tip because it totally goes
with pacing so here is tip five and a
half it's to stop the music this can be
really powerful in your videos if you're
saying something important stopping the
music can let the viewer know what i'm
saying is important and you need to be
listening to me this is definitely great
for certain moments you can pick that
music back up again but when you stop it
it's like an exclamation mark on what
you're saying i was watching last chance
to you basketball in episode one and
they used this technique brilliantly
during the game number 42 kept getting
these calls against him that weren't
really right and he gets angry in storms
off the court the music is building and
building and he heads for the locker
room so check this out
[Music]
yeah that was intense but what they did
here with the editing was totally
amazing the music is building and
building and then he goes into the
locker room he smacks the locker and the
music stops he lets out this big yell
and you can just tell that this is an
intense moment as soon as he hit that
locker the music stops because you know
something shifted you know that he
snapped and i think if they would have
added music to this moment where he
yells and he throws the chair i think it
could have been a little bit cheesy so
stopping the music really was powerful
and it brought me into the screen
wondering what was gonna happen next and
this editing technique that they use on
last chance u you can also do on your
youtube videos once you've finished your
edit inside the software you have all
your videos you have your music files
you have everything ready to go now you
need to export this into one single
video so i'm going to share with you the
best export settings specifically for
youtube so if you're going to upload
this to youtube these are going to be
the best settings that you can do
following google and youtube's
guidelines to get to your export
settings make sure you have your project
selected go to file and then you can go
to share master file or what you can do
is you can come over here to the share
button and then you can also go to
master file by clicking on that right
there so now we have this window and
this is where we're going to get into
all the information i'm going to show
you exactly what you need to do to
upload to youtube specifically to
youtube so right now on info we can see
a few things we can see that our project
is 4k which is great that's what i
wanted at we can see it's at 23.98
frames per second great that's what i
want it as and right here is the file
size so we can see it's a dot mov we can
see that it's 161 megabytes now
sometimes when you first get into here
what you'll notice is right now i've set
to h.264 but usually it's at like an
apple pro does and this is going look
it's like twice the file size this is
going to give you huge file sizes and
it's not even recommended to do this for
youtube it's really not necessary so
what i've been doing for the longest
time is changing my video codec to an
h.264 a lot of people do this it still
works it still goes to youtube it's fine
but this leaves you with a mov well it
turns out youtube actually wants a dot
mp4 so i'm gonna show you how to do that
in final cut pro right now what you need
to do is go to your format and instead
of video and audio what it's just
normally set to you want to go to
computer this is going to change it to a
dot mp4 and this is also still an h.264
file but we're going to go to better
quality because we want the best quality
possible now you can't really mess with
this and and change the quality but
better quality is going to give you the
best quality possible our resolution
that's fine our color space audio format
all this stuff is fine that's all you
have to change is format to computer
make sure you're on better quality and
this is going to give you even a smaller
file and i think why they want a dot mp4
than a mov is because i believe mov runs
more natively on like apple devices
where mp4 is more of a global standard
and all the devices that are android pc
windows all that kind of stuff are going
to run mp4 files even faster so i
believe that your mp4 files once you
upload that to youtube it's actually
going to run faster upload faster on all
devices and so that's great and that's
what you want to do especially when
youtube is recommending that now let me
show you how to save this as a preset so
you don't have to go through all those
steps every single time you can just do
it in one click what you want to do is
go back up here to the share button and
we are actually going to add a
destination because right now when i
click on master file even though i just
change it to an mp4 i go back into my
settings and it's changed back to an
h.264 mov file so we don't want that
we're going to cancel this we are going
to add a new destination and from here
all you really got to do is drag in
export file drag it right there it's
fine if you want it at the very top
that's great as well when you click on
it this is where you can actually change
the preset so format again we're going
to change this to computer we're going
to change this to better quality and
then resolution i like to leave mine at
4k but you can always change that if you
edit in hd what you can also do here
which is cool is change the name so we
can change this to dot mp4
if we want to do that and then once you
hit the close button everything's saved
you don't have to click save you go back
up here you're going to see our mp4 at
the very top we're going to click that
we go to our settings and look
everything is saved and we can hit next
and you can see this actually updated
the resolution to match what my timeline
is at so it's going to do that
automatically which is perfect then
we're going to go to next we can save it
to our desktop or save it to wherever
we'd like and then that is going to
export for you now this next section is
so important it's going to save you from
buying a bunch of hard drives for all
these videos it's also going to save you
from wasting your time and all this
frustration on it we all know videos can
take up a lot of space on our computers
and so you want to dump it onto a hard
drive when you're completely done with
it well the issue with final cut pro 10
is that it holds on to these render
files that makes your library super
large so i'm going to show you how to
reduce that library size and this is
without deleting any videos without
deleting any assets simply by deleting
render files and this is going to save
you a whole lot of space so when you
dump it onto a hard drive you don't have
like 300 gigabytes on the hard drive you
only have like 50. so this is definitely
something that you need to do on every
single project so let me show you how to
save a bunch of space on these library
files once you start editing i haven't
really started this edit yet but once
you do start editing you're going to see
that library just skyrocket and the
gigabytes and the file size is going to
be huge but i'm going to show you right
now how to do that but let me open up a
different library first so in this
project called film yourself in 10 easy
steps this was a video that i did for
think media and in here you can see that
i have my library and it is
377 gigabytes it's absolutely ridiculous
how big it is but i'm going to show you
how to shrink that number down so let's
open up this library so if we select on
the library and we look over here we can
see again it's 377.76
gigabytes and so before we send this to
the external hard drive we want to
shrink that number that's going to save
us a lot of space save us a lot of money
and so that is step number five which is
delete the render files now after doing
a little bit of research i found that
this number is so big because it's
storing all of the render files and
basically what this means is when you're
editing a video and let's say you oh
right here we can see there are these
dots above the timeline this is what
needs to be rendered right now so you
can see all the stuff needs to be
rendered and as that is rendered it's
basically creating more space in that
library so as you can see this is
starting to render but it's actually
going to increase our library space as
that happens and it makes everything
easier to play back but we don't need
that when we're done editing the project
and you can see now the number is going
up because it is starting to render and
we're not editing this project so let's
go ahead and delete our render files how
we do that is we select the library and
then we go up to file and we want to go
to
delete generated library files right
here you're going to have some options
to delete render files and now there's
two options one is to delete the unused
only so any footage that you were
editing that is not now in that final
project it's going to delete those
render files and it can keep all the
render files from the project that
you've already edited however i'm
probably never going to touch this
project again and i want to save more
space and so what i can do is select all
and this is going to delete all the
render files and that's okay it's not
going to delete any video it's not going
to delete any of the assets it's just
deleting kind of like the mock-ups that
final cut makes in order to run faster
and to play back your video quicker one
other thing to note is that you can
still edit this project so let's say we
delete all our render files we throw
onto our hard drive but then we bring it
back and we want to make some more edits
it's totally okay it just needs to
re-render now of course that is going to
then take up more space but when you're
completely done with the project there's
so many projects that i edit that i just
don't ever touch again and so this is my
new method is i just delete all the
render files because if i ever do need
to go back i definitely can and i can
re-render everything so i'm gonna hit
okay and we're gonna see this 378.9
gigabyte file drop but first we need to
go to our event so it can refresh and
then we are going to hit the library
again and look at this it is less than a
gigabyte it is
532.7 megabytes so i'm going to go ahead
and close out final cut pro because i
have auto render on after about five
seconds of not moving the mouse around
it's going to start rendering again and
that's going to add more file size and
you can actually turn that off and mess
with the settings but i'm gonna go ahead
and just close down final cut pro now
that i've closed down final cut pro we
can see here in the film yourself folder
that this library is less than one
gigabyte which is amazing so from here
we have step number six which is to copy
the entire folder onto your external
hard drive so i'm just gonna go ahead
and grab this folder and drag it over my
external hard drive and this is going to
start to copy and the entire project in
its entirety is going to be 76 gigabytes
rather than you know 400 plus gigabytes
so just doing that you know saved us
over 300 gigabytes which is amazing and
then why you see the 76 gigabytes is
from the original raw video that is
inside of that folder under video coming
up in the future we are going to make
more advanced final cut pro 10 tutorials
so let me know down in the comments what
do you want to learn what do you want to
see me cover in the meantime click on
the screen to learn how some of your
favorite youtubers edit their youtube
videos and how you can do the same as
well you're going to learn a whole lot
inside of that video so click on the
screen and i'll see you guys in the next
video
[Music]